Alexander Giovannelli

Phone: +1-740-258-9709Email: agiovannelli@vt.edu Site: https://agiovannelli.github.io/

$\operatorname{Summary}$

My research interest lies in the intersections of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Augmented/Virtual Reality (AR/VR), and 3D User Interfaces (3DUI) for collaboration. I am exploring how to improve asynchronous collaborative processes using immersive technologies. Specifically, I am prototyping and evaluating systems that capture collaborator actions, providing supplemental visuals and interactive mechanisms for future playback.

EDUCATION

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA

Ph.D. in Computer Science advised by Doug A. Bowman, GPA: 4.00/4.00 Aug. 2021-Present

University of Cincinnati Cincinnati, OH, USA

B.S. in Computer Engineering with German Studies minor, GPA: 3.30/4.00 Aug. 2013-May 2018

SKILLS

Programming Languages: C#, JavaScript, Java, Python, HTML, CSS

Productivity Tools: Unity, Git, JMP, SPSS, LaTeX, Tableau

Research Experience

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA Spring 2023 & Fall 2023 Graduate Research Assistant

- Investigated methods for asynchronous and synchronous collaboration in immersive experiences
- Performed contextual inquiry and analysis to determine research goals
- Created prototype virtual reality applications using C# and Unity technologies

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Livermore, CA, USA

Computing Research Intern

Summer 2023

- Developed guided tour prototypes for inspection processes in virtual reality using C# and Unity technologies
- Facilitated meetings between multi-disciplinary project stakeholders
- Prepared user study procedure for evaluation of prototype capabilities

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA Summer 2022

Graduate Research Assistant

- Conducted research regarding communication via avatars in augmented and virtual reality

- Generated prototype applications and experimental studies using C# and Unity technologies
- Designed and administered user studies in accordance with Institutional Review Board regulations

Work Experience

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Columbus, OH, USA Jul. 2018-Jul. 2021

Associate Software Engineer I

- Developed front-end features for Chase.com using JavaScript, HTML, and CSS technologies

- Designed and implemented minimum viable product user interfaces via Figma design tool
- Authored technical documentation for product owners and developers
- Appointed subject matter expert in behavioral-driven development and CI/CD initiatives
- Automated logging of proprietary systems using the Python programming language

Siemens Healthineers

Forchheim, BY, DE

Software Engineer Intern

Jan. 2017-Aug. 2017

- Developed back-end software for use in advanced therapy devices using the C# programming language
- Created system architecture diagrams to record project design changes and behaviors
- Represented project team in international software integration meetings using German and English languages

Granville Exempted Village Schools

Granville, OH, USA

Systems Administrator Intern

May 2016-Jul. 2016

- Provisioned Windows and Linux server and workstation systems to support school network infrastructure
- Administered changes to proprietary devices regarding operating system applications, packages and images
- Managed summer technician team operations

Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

Aug. 2015–Dec. 2015

- Created full-stack internal software tools for engineers and project managers using C#, XML and SQL
- Updated existing project management software according to submitted user feedback
- Authored software usage documents to elaborate on internal tool usage

Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

Aug. 2014-Dec. 2014

- Enhanced existing proprietary software using the C# programming language
- Researched emerging technologies and presented potential process improvements for development team
- Coordinated project design changes with stakeholders

Projects

• Test Environment for Precise Manipulation Tasks

Sept. 2023-Present

Development of existing codebase to provide a study-based execution of precise manipulation experimentation

• Guided Tours for Multiscale Collaborative Virtual Environments

Mar. 2023–Present

Design and prototyping of a virtual environment for collaboration in multiscale inspection processes

• CLUE: An Immersive Competitive Lock-Unlock Experience Development of a gamified experience for Metaverse security using token sequences as an authentication method

Nov. 2022-Mar. 2023

• Virtual Avatar Reaction Visualizations in VR Jun. 2022-Mar. 2023 Development of a virtual environment for user studies investigating avatar reaction visualizations in collaboration

• Surface Generation for MR Remote Collaboration

Jun. 2022-Sept. 2023

Prototyping and testing of multi-user environment for shared surface creation and collaboration

• Environment for Intermittent Typing Experiments in VR

Jan. 2022–May 2022

Creation of a virtual environment with mixed reality capabilities for conducting text-entry user studies

• Smart Lighting Design in Immersive VR

Jan. 2022–Apr. 2022

Development of methods and techniques to support smart real-time lighting design in virtual reality

Clean the Ocean: An Immersive VR Experience

Oct. 2021-Mar. 2022

Creation of a virtual reality experience implementing novel enhancements to classic 3D interaction techniques

Peer Reviewed Journal Papers

1. **A. Giovannelli**, J. Thomas, L. Lane, F. Rodrigues and D. A. Bowman, "Gestures vs. Emojis: Comparing Non-Verbal Reaction Visualizations for Immersive Collaboration," in *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics*, vol. 29, no. 11, pp. 4772-4781, Nov. 2023, doi: 10.1109/TVCG.2023.3320254.

Peer Reviewed Conference Papers

- 2. F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Pavanatto, H. Miao, J. C. d. Oliveira and D. A. Bowman, "AMP-IT and WISDOM: Improving 3D Manipulation for High-Precision Tasks in Virtual Reality," in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), Sydney, Australia, 2023, pp. 303-311, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR59233.2023.00045.
- 3. A. Giovannelli, L. Lisle, and D. A. Bowman, "Exploring the impact of visual information on intermittent typing in virtual reality", in 2022 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), 2022, pp. 8–17, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR55827.2022.00014.

Peer Reviewed Workshops, Posters, Abstracts, & Contests

- 4. I. A. Tahmid, F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Lisle, J. Thomas and D. A. Bowman, "CoLT: Enhancing Collaborative Literature Review Tasks with Synchronous and Asynchronous Awareness Across the Reality-Virtuality Continuum," in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality Adjunct (ISMAR-Adjunct), Sydney, Australia, 2023, pp. 831-836, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR-Adjunct60411.2023.00183.
- A. Giovannelli, F. Rodrigues, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, L. Lane, C. Connor, K. Davidson, G. N. Ramirez, B. David-John, and D. A. Bowman, "Clue hog: An immersive competitive lock-unlock experience using hook on go-go technique for authentication in the metaverse", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 945-946, doi: 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00315.
- 6. J. Thomas, S. W. Lee, **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lane, and D. Bowman, "A communication-focused framework for understanding immersive collaboration experiences", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 301–304, doi: 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00070.
- 7. L. Lisle, F. Lu, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, A. Giovannelli, C. Llo, L. Pavanatto, L. Zhang, L. Schlueter, and D. A. Bowman, "Clean the ocean: An immersive vr experience proposing new modifications to go-go and wim techniques", in 2022 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2022, pp. 920–921, doi: 10.1109/VRW55335.2022.00311.

Awards

• I/ITSEC Leonard P. Gollobin Scholarship	2023
• Davenport Leadership Fellowship	2023 – 2024
• Best IEEE ISMAR 2022 Conference Paper Honorable Mention [3]	2022
• Best 3DUI Contest Entry [7]	2022
• International Co-op Program Scholarship	2016 – 2017
• Matrix Technologies, Inc. Co-op Scholarship	2014 – 2016

TEACHING

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Comparative Languages (CS-3304) Fall 2022

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Software Design & Data Structures (CS-2114) Fall 2021 & Spring 2022

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

•	Communications Chair	2023–Present
	Develop and moderate discussion platforms for the IEEE VR 2024 conference	
•	Student Volunteer	2023
	Assist in event operations at IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality 2023	
•	Student Volunteer	2023
	Assist in event operations at IEEE VR 2023 satellite event in Blacksburg, Virginia	
•	Student Volunteer	2022
	Assist in event operations at IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality 2022	
•	Member of Computer Science Graduate Student Council	2021–Present
	Represent the interests of the CS graduate student body and assist in event planning	
•	Member of the Center for Human-Computer Interaction	2021–Present
	Active participant in the Center seminars regarding the study of human-computer interaction	